[music]
>> Welcome to the world this week.
I'm Joe Lauria, the editor in chief of
Consortium News. This week,
Iran,
war rages, destruction spreads in Iran,
Israel, and on US bases
as the Gulf Arabs reconsider US ties and
the US considers a ground invasion.
At the end of the second week of this
nightmare in the Middle East, we welcome
John Kiriakou, a former CIA officer who
blew the whistle on the agency's torture
program. He's an author, a public
speaker, and a columnist for Consortium
News. John Kiriakou, welcome to the
world this week.
Thank you, Joe.
John, I want to start by talking about
the preparation for this war, I should
say lack of preparation perhaps for this
war. Now, you you were in the agency in
when the lead-up to the invasion of Iraq
began, the last major US
adventure in the region.
Uh tell us what role intelligence
agencies played, like the CIA, like the
Defense Intelligence Agency, uh to
prepare
a country to go to a war on this scale.
And what do you remember from that
period if you had any involvement?
Jordan. Sure. DIA, the Defense
Intelligence Agency, takes the lead in
um
in
bringing together a list of potential
targets. Then they share that
that list with CIA military analysts.
The CIA military, political, and
economic analysts prepare
uh analyses for the president, the
secretary of state, and the secretary of
defense, the national security advisor,
uh
trying to more or less predict what the
responses are going to be from the
Iranian leadership, the Iranian
government, the Iranian oil sector, the
intelligence service, etc., etc. And
then operationally, the CIA
in the lead-up to the to the war and
immediate af- and the immediate
aftermath of the
initial attacks is trying to recruit
Iranian ambassadors, Iranian
intelligence service uh
station chiefs around the world, um
anybody inside the IRGC to try to get
that inside information and disrupt the
decision-making process. But Joe, I
can't help but to think that this
this time was much different. You know,
you hear a lot about off-the-shelf, what
are called off-the-shelf war plans. And
certainly, there are plans to invade
almost every country in the world. They
can just
pull them off the shelf and implement
them
and then they're updated every year. It
seems like there was just simply no plan
this time. They this was done almost on
a whim and it was done in a way that
seriously damaged American credibility
in that we engaged the Iranians in
apparently in talks to to
head off
an armed conflict and instead we just
use that as cover
to keep them back on their heels so that
they wouldn't expect the invasion not
invasion but the attack that eventually
came. Joe, I happen to be in
in Abu Dhabi and Dubai just a few days
before the attack and I met with
I met with both government ministers and
with very senior members of the royal
family and they all asked me the same
thing.
They said
do you think he's going to attack?
Because we genuinely don't know. Wait a
minute, you're talking about now? Trump
you're talking about? Not the
not 2003. Okay. Right. Sorry about that.
So just a few weeks ago they asked me do
you think he'll he'll actually attack?
We don't know because you'll recall a
year ago Donald Trump dismissed dozens
and dozens of career ambassadors.
Non-partisan
professional diplomats dismissed them
all and has never replaced them. There
is no American ambassador in Abu Dhabi.
There is no American ambassador in
Bahrain. There is no American ambassador
in Kuwait or in Dubai. They're gone.
Those positions are vacant and so
there's no dialogue going back and forth
between these ostensible allies.
And so they genuinely don't have any
idea what the White House is planning to
do.
Are there any military attaches in these
embassies that are that are functioning?
There are, but military attaches belong
to the defense attache program, which is
an intelligence collection
position. They aren't there to offer
intelligence. They're there to collect
it. And then there's something called
FMC, foreign military I forget what.
It's They're there just to sell weapons
and weapon systems.
So, the diplomacy has to has to be done
at the ambassadorial level, or if
there's no ambassador at the charge
d'affaires level, but the charge
d'affaires is whoever happens to be the
senior most person in the embassy, and
it can change from day to day. This is
no way to run a war. It's no way to run
a State Department.
So, this kind of preparation that you
discussed should take place.
Should be First of all, as you said, the
plans are They're already there, but
they have to be brushed off. And they
have to be put into action, and that
should be months before any kind of
action. And as far as you know,
very little of that, if anything, was
done.
Yeah, in fact, in
in 2003,
um we we started planning the Iraq War
like in earnest, planning the Iraq War,
building staffs,
um doing analyses, moving equipment 10
months before we invaded Iraq. And it
was clear what we were going to do,
because we had the Secretary of State
just dashing all around the world to to
bring allies into line. There was this
policy called burden sharing, where we
went to every single one of the Arab
Gulf countries and uh and got them to
pay in advance for for the start of the
war. None of that happened this uh this
month. None of that. And on top of that,
President Bush, politically,
in 2003
and very early 2004, crisscrossed the
country trying to to whip up public
support for an attack on Iraq.
President Bush hasn't left the White
House except to go to Mar-a-Lago or to
go golfing.
Yeah, well, his father got went to the
UN Security Council and got a resolution
to authorize in the chapter 7, the first
Gulf War. He put together a coalition of
about 30 countries, I think.
Um and uh and he went to Congress and
got got a resolution there. And he made
speeches across the country, at least
two or three major speeches to get
public support.
He had a reason, at least.
Even some of us disagreed with that war,
but it wasn't invasion of another
country. I think that April Glaspie, the
American ambassador there,
signaled to Saddam that uh US wouldn't
do anything if he invaded. May have been
a trap he was set. That's something we
can discuss another time. Then in the
second in second Gulf War, George W.
Bush uh made speeches across the
country, told a bunch of lies about WMD,
went to the UN Security Council, didn't
get a resolution, but invaded anyway,
and then went to Congress and did get a
resolution, and had three countries in
this coalition, which was Poland,
Australia, and the US.
And
and then Europe opposes, we know French
and Germans on the Security Council did
not agree. Uh and this time none of this
has happened. But what did happen, John,
is that over the last 30 40 years since
the revolution in 1979 in Iran, the US
has game planned a war of this scale
against Iran, and it seems like they
came back with the understanding that
what would happen if the US invaded Iran
is what we're seeing playing out right
now. And therefore, no president until
this one,
despite the pressure from not only
Netanyahu, but also the Saudi leadership
as well, I think, at certain points
anyway, to do this, the they resisted
Israel's pressure, which is not
something you often see in the United
States government. What happened this
time, John? What is different about this
president? Why did he do what no
president would do before?
I can tell you what the rumor is at the
White House. The rumor is that Benjamin
Netanyahu told Trump, "If you don't do
it, I'm going to use nuclear weapons."
And that Trump decided to do it to head
off an Israeli use of nuclear weapons.
Now, with that said, um I spoke with a
friend of ours, yours and mine, last
night at over dinner, a friend who knows
these issues very deeply. And he said
that he was convinced that Trump did it
because he wants
to normalize the use of nuclear weapons,
that he intends to use a nuclear weapon.
I know I I disagreed, uh but he he was
pretty confident in in his analysis. I
think what happened here, Joe,
is that
Donald Trump,
Marco Rubio, and Pete Hegseth somehow
convinced themselves, probably because
this was Netanyahu's analytic line, that
as soon as the first rocket was fired,
the Iranian government would collapse
like a house of cards.
And that was never going to happen.
Never. Look at it this way, too. Iran is
the size of the whole of Western Europe.
It's surrounded by forbidding mountains
on three sides.
And it has 92 million people, and you
can't overthrow a government like that
with 25 or 50,000 troops and two
aircraft carriers.
I was shaking my head before, not
because I didn't believe that he wants
to normalize, but that that is he might
want to do that. I was I didn't believe
he would do it.
>> Um
>> Yeah. What about the idea There's
another reason Max Blumenthal at The
Grayzone has written that the FBI worked
with Israel to create this idea that uh
and to put in Trump's head that the
supreme egotist that they the Iranians
try to kill him a couple of times which
there's really no evidence for. So that
might be part of it and then there's the
old standby right now which is don't
forget Jeffrey Epstein.
I don't want to talk about Epstein in
this show except to say that we've had
the former military intelligence officer
Ari Ben-Menashe on our program and he's
told us and others that he believes that
>> Israelis have the entire unredacted
files whether they got it directly from
from Epstein himself working for them or
they hacked into it. They've got it and
that as he could have
and Netanyahu met many times over to
Mar-a-Lago and the White House suggested
that this could be winding up on the
front page of the New York Times if
certain thing doesn't happen like
invading like bombing and attacking
Iran. I think that's a possibility as
well. So there are these different
reasons all amount to blackmail
basically. Um
which something Israel's probably pretty
well known for. So this is not a big
deal.
This could very well have been the case
but that nonetheless it happened and
there wasn't this preparation. There
wasn't an attempt also to turn I
remember in the um
I think in the invasion 2003 there were
they they were able to turn a bunch of
high-level Iraqi intelligence people
maybe military people. That didn't
happen here, did it? No one within Iran
that we know of No that that didn't
happen here. And you know I think one of
the reasons why that didn't happen here
is that um
the Israelis
killed everybody. I mean they've they've
essentially decapitated the the Iraq the
Iranian nuclear program. They they
killed almost every member of the senior
military command. Uh I think that uh
that that has actually inspired the
remaining officials uh to to fight to
the death just for their own honor, the
honor of their country. Uh I don't think
anybody wants to be in the in the pay of
the Israeli intelligence service. I
mean, no no right-thinking Iranian
would. Um it was different for the
Iraqis.
They genuinely hated and feared Saddam
Hussein. And while they considered us to
be invaders and occupiers, um they knew
that we wouldn't execute them were they
to switch sides. And that's why we had
the, you know, the Iraqi ambassador to
the United Nations uh defect to Canada.
The Iraqi ambassador to the United
States defected to the UK. The Iraqi
ambassadors all over the country. I
worked I
I worked personally on Iraqi
intelligence service station chiefs who
were practically lined up to come over
to the side of the CIA. That is not
happening this time around.
Another thing that's different is on the
ground. If you
I I I recall a lot of Amer- Iraqi
soldiers turned around and didn't fight
for Saddam. And they were shot in the
back. Thank you very much by the United
States, the famous turkey shoot, of
course. One of the more disgraceful
episodes in the long history of
disgraceful
behavior by the United States in abroad
and also
Yeah, they buried alive. You know, you
may not remember this. It was a front
page, I think, on the one of the New
York tabloids at the time. They buried
some Iraqi soldiers alive with
bulldozers in their
in in the sand. They just bulldozed
people. Well, so they didn't fight. They
ran. Uh there was a civil war later, and
that's a very complicated story in Iraq.
But I think Iraqis they don't understand
anything about Iran or the especially
this group.
And that goes back to intelligence
again. But I think if you look at the
conduct of the Iranian people and state
during the Iran-Iraq War, which was
imposed on them by the United States
backing Saddam to try to put down the
revolution. Look at the way they fought.
The hundreds of thousands of young men
who died defending Iran and they fought
Iraq but armed by the US. Both sides
were armed to some degree
to deplete both sides but they they held
Iraq to a standoff. So this is a
different
situation. They did they did did they
expect do you think
did did they expect in the White House
that the Iraqis would just lay down? You
said that that they would lay down their
arms that they would not fight back. How
could they?
You know Joe I I'm I'm amazed even at
the mainstream media outlets here that
sort of reinforced this false White
House analysis where CNN for days
after we started the attack
would show clips from the same
demonstration in Los Angeles of between
200 and 300 people waving the flags from
the time of the Shah of Iran. Most of
the Iranians that that went from Iran to
Southern California happen to be Jewish.
These are not
sort of mainstream Iranian Iranians.
They're royalists.
They're not Muslim.
They identify primarily as Americans.
And if you're taking your cue from these
people you're in for a rude awakening
and I think that's what happened. You
know even even commentators on the likes
of CNN and MS now were saying well you
know there was this large demonstration
in Los Angeles. No actually there
wasn't. It was 200 or 300 people.
This is ridiculous.
They did the same thing inside Iran. I
think there was a picture of a small
celebration when the Ayatollah was
killed in Iran and they you never you
never got a wide shot to see how much
how many people were there.
That's right.
>> celebrating but but how this goes back
to the intelligence question. Is Is that
they they don't exist?
There aren't people who are specialists
in Iran at the agency or at the DIA who
who understand the country and how they
would react and what was needed to
prepare to do such a hairbrained scheme
like this to unleash what did they have
unleashed or is it there wasn't they
weren't listened to?
Yeah, I I will admit to you that my that
my information is dated. I left the CIA
quite some time ago, but
I assume that [clears throat]
the caliber of of analysts are the same
as they were
20 years ago when I was there and they
were outstanding.
They knew as much about Iran and Iranian
culture and Iranian politics and Iranian
history as as anybody in any, you know,
foreign country or think tank or or
university. Um, my guess is that the
White House just decided they had a
policy and they didn't care what the
intelligence said. And God knows we've
seen that in other countries around the
world.
So, I think that's what it was. They
just made a a decision. They're going to
do this. It's going to be easy because
it it's going to fall like a house of
cards. Everybody hates the Ayatollahs.
They're they're
dying for freedom. They'll welcome us as
liberators. It's the same nonsense we
heard um from the neocons in the run-up
to the Iraq war. I I've told the story
many times. I think it bears repeating
here
that uh the night before we invaded
Iraq, I was
CIA Director George Tenet's note-taker
in what's what was called a principals
committee meeting. It was the final
principals committee meeting. The
principals committee is usually chaired
by the president. In this case, the
president was off doing something, so it
was chaired by Vice President Cheney.
And other attendees were
uh National Security Advisor Condoleezza
Rice and her note-taker, two or three
NSC officials,
uh Secretary of State Colin Powell and
his note taker, the chairman and vice
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
and their note taker,
um, General Tommy Franks, the head of
CENTCOM, and his note taker, and George
and me. And, uh, the vice president
kicked off the meeting by saying, uh,
"General Franks, why don't you give us
an order of battle briefing?" I always
hated these order of battle briefings
because they're so boring and they mean
nothing to me. I don't care where the
little men are moving on the map. I
don't care if elements of the second
mountain division are moving here and
the armored division's moving there. I
don't care.
They're going to change in an hour
anyway. So,
at the very end of the briefing,
General Franks said, quote,
"If all goes as planned, we can be in
Tehran by August."
And George George very discreetly shut
off his microphone and he turned to me
and he said, "Did he say Baghdad or did
he say Tehran?"
And I said, "He said Tehran."
And then George turned the microphone
back on. At the end of the meeting, I
went back to my office and the deputy
director asked me, "How did the meeting
go?"
And I said, "Did you know we were going
to attack Iran?"
And he said,
"Are they still talking about that?
We're not going to attack Iran."
And I said, "Do these people know
nothing about history?" And he said,
"No, they know nothing about history."
And now we have history repeating itself
23 years later.
You mean that was a Freudian slip?
Oh, no, it wasn't Freudian at all. The
plan was and and this this was the
cherry on top. As we got up to walk out
of the meeting, one of these stooges
from the NSC said, "When we cross that
border tomorrow, they're going to throw
flowers at us."
And
it was the same attitude 2 weeks ago
that we would be seen as liberators.
They would throw flowers at us.
And it's like no, nobody in the Middle
East will ever see us as liberators.
They see us as invaders and occupiers
and thieves of their natural resources.
We're not going to be greeted as
liberators.
And we haven't been.
So the person who was telling Trump that
that's going to be a cakewalk
essentially had to be Netanyahu because
uh you It had to be. Nobody else.
>> Netanyahu with Rubio and Hegseth nodding
their heads like bobbleheads. Well,
that's the thing. We have a collection
of numbskulls and amateurs and fanatics.
And I have to I want to talk to you a
little bit about Hegseth because this is
a creature that I have never seen in
government before. I met people kind of
like that in the United States. I know
there are American men with this type of
gung-ho I mean over-the-top gung-ho
mania, but this guy just takes the cake.
But so if Netanyahu said on the record
when about a day after this
operation began, he said he's been
waiting 40 years for this. So he
admitted he's been trying for 40
>> I Joe, I've said I've said
for decades now. And I've been saying a
lot the last couple of weeks.
Every single Israeli prime minister
for the last 40 years
in every single visit to the White House
over 40 years has asked us to attack
Iran. And every single president has
said no until Donald Trump. Right. And
they said no, the American presidents
because they saw that the Strait of
Hormuz would be closed and oil prices
would skyrocket and the world economy
would be imperiled, that American bases
in the region could actually be hit,
that Israel
this is not a Panama in 1989 that
they've invaded here.
Right. This is a substantial enemy.
Usually um
the Americans have become famous for
only attacking countries that are weaker
than they are, much weaker than they
are, that can't put up a fight. This
time
they have chosen someone who has put can
put up a fight and is doing that. So, I
want to So, before I ask you about the
course of the war right now,
uh what is actually happen What do we
know is really happening and where do we
think this is headed? I want to talk a
little bit about Hex it. Do you ever
know anybody
in because I just I can't watch the guy,
but I did read his transcript this
morning of the press given one every I I
wasn't even reading them because I saw a
little I just can't deal with it. But,
he was saying this is not a fair fight.
We're killing them. We're destroying
them. He's making it sound like this is
the cakewalk that they thought that it
was, except it's day 14, it's going to
be day 15, it's going to be And after a
while, this is not a cakewalk anymore.
And And they're going to have to start
reckoning well, what the hell's really
happening here. But, let me ask you
about the character of this Hex it, the
guy who is a religious fanatic who said
at this press conference this morning,
Saturday, that he God is number one up
there, right? I
Now, I can't remember he put the
Constitution or Trump next, but you
know, God is number one. That's who he's
allegiance to. And in a press conference
explaining to the world
what the US is doing. Have you known
anybody in I doubt there would be
anybody in the agency like this, but
these are only types in the military,
right?
>> Not in the agency.
Yeah.
>> Yeah, and you remember you remember some
years ago,
um
during the Obama administration, there
was a Lieutenant General retired General
who retired and went into business um
making uh scopes for sniper rifles. And
on the inside of the scope, you could
only see it if it was right up against
your eye, it would say something like um
uh
"For God so loved the world that he gave
his only begotten son." And it's like,
well, now what do we do? Do we have to
recall the the sniper scopes?
Uh because this nut decided to etch this
on the on the glass of the scope. Um,
you know, one funny thing about Hexseth,
he he made me chuckle as you were
describing him.
He was challenged by a reporter last
week uh about some of his uh some of his
assertions that were just rolling right
over the Iranians. And his response was,
"Yeah, that's what your mother said last
night when I was leaving her house."
You know, what what
we're in the Twilight Zone, Joe.
We're in the Twilight Zone.
That a senior official would even think
to say something like that, let alone
actually verbalize it. But the guy is a
religious extremist, which hasn't kept
him from cheating on two of the three of
his wives that we know of so far. He has
white supremacist tattoos that he's
quite proud of. He works out with in the
Pentagon without his shirt on and shows
off his white supremacist tattoos.
Um, and you know, he's one of these guys
that
I'm going to just going to come out and
say it. He's just not smart enough to
know the difference between MAGA
Republicanism and neo-conservative
Republicanism because his conclusion is
that MAGA is whatever Donald Trump says
it is today. And if that means
no war during the campaign, then by God,
it's going to be no war. And if it means
attack Iran just because Benjamin
Netanyahu said so, then by God, we're
going to attack Iran.
And so, the country's in a state of
confusion, the the the financial markets
are in a state of confusion, oil is well
over $100 a barrel now, it's going to
$200 a barrel, and now Barron's magazine
or Barron's newspaper, I got it right
here, is telling us to invest in four
companies that build robots
to find underwater mines.
That's what it's come to.
It's a little too late to build those
robots, I would say.
I think you're right.
So, you know, I underestimated this guy,
Hexseth, because I I saw him as a macho
idiot and he didn't totally unqualified
for this job and he he had that
embarrassing thing where they spent a
lot of our taxpayers money to bring all
the generals from around the world in
this room to be
lectured and I mean it must been so
embarrassing. But so this but I didn't
think he was full of this venom, this
kind of insanity and this blood lust. I
know
Gloria ethic and all that but I didn't
think he'd actually put this into play
like that. And that's my fault for not
realizing that he was this bad.
Yeah, and you know another thing that
that bothers me very much. You and I
both have friends in Iran or who have
traveled to Iran. My partner is an
Iranian-American who visits Iran
regularly.
Any of these people
could have said, "This is not going to
work. This is not a viable policy." And
you know you said something
a few minutes ago about um
sanctions and the fact that Iran has had
sanctions on it for 47 years. The
Iranians are extremely resourceful
people and anybody who's been to Iran
will tell you that if the Iranians need
something, they'll make it. If they
can't buy it, they'll manufacture it and
that they lack for literally nothing.
Let's well, I think they're going to be
pretty good at making missiles and
drones and underwater and submarines and
speedboats and a whole bunch of
hypersonic missiles.
A lot of which they haven't used yet.
Let's talk about how this war is going.
Um
you're not surprised that Iran has been
able to fight back so badly and so well,
have you are you?
No, I'm not surprised at all and I think
that that it was all part of a of a
bigger plan where well, you know what?
It's not that John thinks so cuz John's
so smart. It's because of the Israeli
leadership has come right out and said
it that once Iran is is defeated and
pacified, the Israelis are going to turn
and look at Turkey. I happen to have
dinner a couple of nights ago with the
Turkish Deputy Foreign Minister.
And I said to him, "What What would
Turkey do if the Israelis decided that
they wanted, you know, a hotter conflict
between the two countries?" I said,
"Oddly enough, if Israel attacks Turkey,
Turkey being a NATO country, the United
States would have to come in on the side
of Turkey and would have to fight
Israel." Now, you and I both know that
that's never going to happen.
And he said very confidently
that
the Turks would not invoke Article 5,
that the Turks would wipe out Israel,
hm, and they wouldn't need anybody's
help to protect them.
That they're not afraid of this this
tiny country
to their south. They're not afraid of
the Israelis.
That's interesting. If they did invoke
Article 5, maybe Spain would go and help
them because Spain. Yeah, maybe Spain.
And that's it.
So,
tell me about what you know about the
what the how the war has been going.
There's no information coming out of
very little anyway coming out of Israel
about what damage they're actually
suffering. If you look at the Haaretz
newspaper,
Yeah, so heavy. We're learning nothing.
Yeah, you look at Haaretz and it every 5
minutes on their update is sirens heard
in Galilee, sirens heard in the gap,
sirens heard in Haifa. And then no
reporting. What happened?
What happened after those sirens? So,
there was a video that came out
yesterday, you may have seen it. It's
quite long and it's It's one of the
airbases and it's getting quite a lot of
heavy fire. Um, so there's obviously
damage going on there. There was a
report this morning that an Israeli
general, I believe, was saying let
Netanyahu and Trump should say they won,
just declare victory, and let everything
stay. Don't lift sanctions, don't change
anything, go back to the status quo
ante. Now, that tells you that there are
people in Israel who realize we can't
take this anymore and we're running low
on interceptor missiles and we better
put an end to this. Except, Iran has a
say in this and they last time in June
of last year, as we know, the US asked
for a ceasefire because the Israelis
asked for the same reasons they were
running low on the interceptors. The US
went through a third of the THAAD
missiles and the Israeli interceptors
were going and Iran agreed. This time
they said they won't. They won't agree.
This is situation we're in, right? And
they shouldn't agree. I I heard
yesterday that the United States and
Israel have used so far in the last 2
weeks more Patriot missiles than the
Ukrainians have used in the last 4
years.
There aren't any more Patriot missiles.
We can't make them fast enough. And as
you noted a moment ago,
the Iranians have not yet used their
hypersonics. You know, so many of us
were afraid that they might use it
against the USS Abraham Lincoln or the
USS Gerald R. Ford aircraft carriers.
Why would they now? They would be better
off sending these five or ten thousand
dollar, you know, cheap suicide drones
to Israel, let the Israelis exhaust
their supply of defensive weapons,
and then send hypersonics to Dimona and
and Tel Aviv. That's what I would do.
And I think that's exactly what the
Israelis are afraid the Iranians might
do. Now, the US reached out a week ago
to the Italians and asked the Italians
to weigh in with the Iranians. The
Iranians ignored us. So, day before
yesterday we went back to the Omanis and
asked the Omanis to engage with the
Iranians. The Iranians came back and
said, "We have demands.
Uh an immediate ceasefire before talks
even start.
Uh they want um
uh the US to pull all all bases out of
the Middle East, which of course is a
non-starter.
Um, they want sanctions lifted. And the
fourth one was, uh,
oh, $25 billion in reparations.
So, there won't be any ceasefire talks.
And it's because the Iranians don't need
for there to be ceasefire talks.
No demands for the, for nothing for the
Palestinians.
Nothing for the Palestinians.
>> Yeah.
So, Iran would be in the driver's seat
if they deplete all the interceptors.
Israel will lie, lie before them
vulnerable and open. At that point they
can dictate the terms. They may even
increase some from what you just said.
But that would be for starters right
there. And when you kill the supreme
leader like that, which was the
biggest mistake they could have made on
the first day, let alone killing the
school children. Um, how do you expect
Iran to say, "Okay, we'll agree to a
ceasefire at this time?" This is all-out
war. They've prepared for it. They wish
not to have to do this, but they are
implementing it right now. And you see
the enormous courage of the Iranian
people standing in the street on Al-Quds
Day on Friday
with bombs
bursting nearby. Now, you have to
believe that the Israelis or the
Americans, whoever were doing that,
could have hit the crowds. They didn't,
but they were trying to scare the hell
out of them and they did not scare,
John. Those are some of the most
extraordinary things you could see.
I saw that video yesterday and, uh, and
today and it really is remarkable.
They're not afraid.
They're not afraid to die for their
country. They're just not. And, and
another thing, too, is they're, they're
they're so well
read
uh, on these issues, on these foreign
policy issues. I don't think there was a
single Iranian out of the 92 million of
them that was surprised when we began
this attack. They've been expecting it.
They expect behavior like this from the
United States and Israel.
And you said now that you don't think
the it's a it's a non-starter you said
for the US to remove its bases. But what
we've learned now from satellite
imagery, which even the New York Times
did a piece on,
there's been extensive damage to a
number of the US bases in the region.
The Arab
monarchies
in the Gulf made a deal going way back
to FDR on that boat in the Suez with the
King Saudi King that you will provide
oil to us with buying it in dollars and
we will give you security. Basically,
that's the deal and they made that deal
with all of the Gulf
monarchies in which the British set up
by the way and the deal was that
you have local autonomy, but Britain
would run the foreign policy and the
defense of these five countries in the
in the Gulf region. And of course, the
US just took that over. Basically,
that's the same deal. The US runs the
foreign policy and the defense. They
were not defended, John. The you've seen
this letter from this Al Habtoor, this
billionaire in the UAE. You've seen
Reuters had a big piece the other day
about how they're reconsidering their
relationship with the United States
because the deal didn't work. They
weren't defended. They didn't
We talked about the lack of preparation.
Clearly, these monarchies were not
informed enough that what would happen,
what could happen if the US went to war
against Iran, but they everybody knew
that this is what Iran could do and they
dragged these guys into it. Now, what do
you about the relationship between the
Gulf Arab states and the US after this?
Yeah, like I said, I was in the Gulf
2 and 1/2 weeks ago and another 2 weeks
before that.
I went to I went to
Kuwait, Qatar and the United Arab
Emirates, Abu Dhabi, and Dubai.
And and they come right out and say
exactly the same thing, Joe, that the
deal is
they were going to host these bases,
which include the headquarters of the
Fifth Fleet in Bahrain. They include Al
Udeid Airbase in Qatar, which is the
largest airbase in the world.
As many as 25,000 troops in Kuwait,
another 15,000 or so troops in the
United Arab Emirates.
And the idea was all of those
installations and and personnel are
supposed to protect these countries. And
we haven't we haven't protected them.
Everybody's been hit. Airports have been
destroyed in Kuwait and Bahrain.
Um the hotels in in Dubai are being hit,
which is going to cost a fortune in
terms of economic loss.
Um and and uh
uh
I forget the economic term. Anyway,
the this is what the Wall Street
Journal's reporting. And
um and in in Doha, this gigantic
The the Iranians are able to hit it at
will.
And so I think every one of these these
royal or ruling, in the case of Kuwait,
families
um are going to have to reconsider the
relationship, at least renegotiate the
relationship.
Um so it's I don't think it's out of the
realm of possibility that they'll ask
the US to leave and maybe look towards
Iran for protection, not only from the
United States, but from Israel. Israel
is the threat to these countries. Not
Iran, basically. I think that maybe
they're starting to wake up to that.
They've made their deals and their peace
without a formal peace treaty with
Israel, without the stupid Abraham
Accords. But we've known that there was
a story the other day that about five
the first 5,000 Israelis from Dubai were
being flown out. So who knew that there
were at least that many and there were
many more.
>> Yeah, I had no idea. No idea there were
that many Israelis in Dubai. I was
shocked by that number. And now um
they're they're landing by the 747 load
in Cyprus
to the point where
a Cypriot contact of mine told me just
day before yesterday, there are street
signs in Hebrew now, there are menus in
Hebrew, there are Hebrew-speaking real
estate agents. They're all going to
Cyprus.
And that's in the last
in the last months then or years? Yeah,
now Recently.
>> Yeah, just just since August. This has
been going on since August.
In Greece
in Athens specifically,
there's been a real run-up in real
estate prices, not because the Greek
economy is any good, but because
Israelis are all buying the real estate
there and and driving prices up.
So where does this go, John? Where does
this war lead to if it continues the way
it is right now and they run out of the
missiles and by the way by the radar
those very expensive radar that were
taken out, they can't use the THAAD
missiles I understand to
bring down 50 minutes.
Um
this goes on for another 2 weeks. Where
do you Where do you see this war being
if let's say it goes another 2 weeks?
Where are we going to be at? I honestly
believe
that at the end of this Donald Trump is
just going to declare victory and go
home.
And leave the wreckage for the next
president whoever that happens to be. I
really think that's what he's going to
do. He's going to say we won, we crushed
them, we allowed this Ayatollah to
remain in in power, and we've we've
cowed this government, and they're going
to do what we say, so we've we've won
this thing and we're going to go home.
Well, if I were the Iranians,
the very first thing I would do is to
seek a nuclear weapon. You somebody said
to me the other day, and this was so
simple and so powerful, we're not
talking right now about North Korea. Do
you know why? Because North Korea has a
nuclear weapon.
Iran needs one.
Well, they might change the man that who
put out the fatwa against it has been
killed on the opening hours. That's
right.
of this war.
Um what about the idea of a ground
invasion? There's a lot of talk still
about that. First it was going to be the
Kurds from the north, but they wised up
it seems like the Kurds. They uh know
the history of how the US and other
Western governments have used the Kurds
for short-term interests and then kicked
them to the curb once they were not no
longer needed. They were very much the
way the British did with all the Arabs
in the First World War to fight against
Turkey. But um
they wised up. They said we're not going
in unless the US is with us. Well, that
talk died down pretty quickly. But now
there's this expeditionary force of
2,500 Marines [clears throat] on the USS
Tripoli go being sent. And what is that?
Is that just optics? Is that just or is
there really something being planned
here? What what could they do with 2,500
Marines?
Almost nothing except protect American
embassies.
Ah.
>> That's just about it. Yeah. Yeah, you
can't do 2,500 Marines against 92
million Iranians.
I mean, it's laughable that we're even
having this conversation. No planning
went into this at all. No planning. You
remember Joe in 1990,
August 2nd, 1990, Iraq invaded and
occupied Kuwait. And we sent 565,000
troops to the Gulf.
565,000,
not 2,500 Marines.
And not a couple of plane loads of, you
know, THAAD systems.
565,000
ground troops and six aircraft carrier
strike groups.
Well, this what we're doing now is like
a like a a joke.
We can't do anything with two aircraft
carriers, 22 ships, with two more on the
way, 2,500 Marines, maybe 40, maybe
50,000 ground troops who have never, you
know,
who have never left base except to go
into town to do some shopping.
So, what's that going to do for us?
We can't overthrow the Iranian
government and occupy a country that's
the size of Western Europe with 40 or
50,000 troops.
That's how many are in the region now,
50,000 apparently. Or 52,500 when the
Marines arrive.
It's a joke.
>> [laughter]
>> It's an absolute absolute joke, but this
entire administration is a joke. And
that Netanyahu found the saps that he's
been waiting for to for them to do this.
Yes.
>> and he's imperiled his own country, Iran
Israel. The smoke will clear, we'll
learn about the damage that's been done,
and it's not over yet. And uh
I I just want to look What do you think
the Middle East is going to look like
when this is over?
You know, odd as this sounds, I think it
probably is going to look the same. And
the reason I say that is Here, we used
to use this term in our CIA analysis,
muddling through.
That these governments, these countries,
they always seem to just muddle through
these catastrophic problems. If you look
at the at the first Gulf War, Joe,
literally none of the leaders changed.
You have Iraq attack Kuwait, and 565,000
troops push him out, and wipe out the
Iraqi military, and Yasser Arafat
endorsed Saddam, and Ali Abdullah Saleh
in in Yemen endorsed Saddam.
And then, when the last shot was fired,
everybody just kind of went back to
their palaces and and everything was
exactly the same.
I think that's what we're going to see
here, too.
That everybody's just going to muddle
through. We may see, as we said, this
questioning of of the value of having
the US military in such big numbers,
heavy presences in these countries. Um
and and this might all be part of a slow
decline of American hegemony in the
region, whether it's military or
economic or both.
But I think in the in the near term, we
shouldn't expect to see much in the way
of change.
So, the US will rebuild these
billion-dollar radar systems and rebuild
the bases the way they were before?
Well, Max Blumenthal reported today that
uh
the end-of-the-year budget for the
Pentagon last year, millions and
millions of dollars were spent on
uh lobster dinners and uh cracked crab
because you had to you have to spend the
money uh at the end of the fiscal year.
So, there's money there. Every year,
Congress approves appropriates more
money than the Pentagon asks for.
And they have to spend it on something.
I think they'll just rebuild. But the
Gulf states will say, "Uh we're not
certain we want these targets here,
Admiral, because you didn't protect us.
And now you're just a target on our
back." Mhm.
>> [clears throat]
>> I think that's going to be the big
problem. It's going to be a diplomatic
one. Yes.
Yeah. And uh because Iran is going to
First of all, when are they going to
give up? They may go all the way for the
kill because they're in the driver's
seat. They will be shortly if those
interceptors run out and there's no no
ground invasion. And there's no will
They the will of the country is strong
to keep fighting, it looks like. Um
so, that
will Iran, you know, how could Iran
cannot allow the status quo to remain
because they will rebuild and rearm,
like you just said, and attack them
again, maybe. And in Trump's he's got 3
more years left. I mean, God help us,
but there's three more years of this
Trump administration. Now, our future
president may realize don't go after
Iran like the previous presidents did.
But, we slept three years with this guy.
Yeah, we do.
We do, and he's so unpredictable.
And I think that
I think that one of the most dangerous
figures in this whole equation is Marco
Rubio. Marco Rubio is an old-style
neo-conservative
communist-hating
And that hatred of communism extends to
to Islam.
And I think that like, you know, John
McCain before him and Barry Goldwater
and and so many of the others that have,
you know,
that have for years made up the
Republican Party's uh foreign policy and
defense establishment, he's a true
believer. This guy is a serious problem.
And don't forget Lindsey Graham. Uh
everyone
>> Graham Oh, but Lindsey Graham is such a
clown. I I have trouble
wrapping my brain around the idea that
people actually take him seriously.
You remember his sidekick
Sorry, go ahead.
Yeah, but they do, and he's perfectly
He's perfectly happy to send your son
and my son and anybody else's son off to
die for Israel.
You remember his sidekick John McCain
singing bomb bomb bomb bomb bomb Iran
to the Beach Boys song Wouldn't It Be
Nice.
He got what he wanted. Um
Yeah.
I I think
rebuilding the bases will just invite
another attack from Iran. So, I I I
let's move on to the BRICS issue because
this war is not just about Israel and US
and Iran.
And Iran is a member of BRICS. This is a
front line in a worldwide movement right
now to
to resist the US dominance in the world.
And what we're seeing this war is about
is not only greater Israel, but greater
America. The an American global empire
and a regional Israeli empire. This is
what the logic of this war is. So, Iran
is
a wall that the empire is hitting
against right now. This could be one of
the most historic
uh wars uh in our lifetime, much more
than the first two Gulf wars. This could
be because of what's behind Iran,
Russia, China, and the entire
global south really, or the BRICS
matters, who are trying to resist and
have a world where people are uh
countries relate to each other more or
less in an equal manner, and resist one
unipolar power, the United States. So,
what about this the the role of not only
is the Iran war so historically
important, but this battle on Strait of
Hormuz could be a battle talked about
for centuries.
Oh, yeah. If it happens, if it happens.
You know, I I think it's funny in in the
in the mainstream media, we hear
these comparisons to um
to the Iranian threat to close the
Strait of Hormuz back in the middle
1980s, and Ronald Reagan sent naval
escorts to to escort these oil tankers.
That you might remember the SS Bridgeton
was hit. It was the biggest oil tanker
in the world at the time. It burned for
weeks, and Reagan sent these ships to
escort
um ship cargo ships out.
It's not the 1980s anymore.
The technology is far advanced.
Uh it's not just mines that ships have
to worry about. There aren't enough
ships in the US Navy to escort
all of the oil tankers and all of the
cargo ships that need to go in and out
of the Gulf.
And so, this is another thing Joe also
that I I think the administration just
hasn't really given thought to. Now,
getting to BRICS,
I agree with you. BRICS
BRICS ought to be an existential threat
to the United States
because these are some of the
the biggest countries in the world
they're some of the biggest economies in
the world. They include the economic
powerhouses of the global south
like South Africa and Brazil for
example.
And they're talking about and granted
this is years away but they're talking
about a unified currency.
Well, if there's a a unified BRICS
currency
you think the Chinese and the Russians
and the Indians are are going to want to
carry out
international trade in US dollars? Why
would they?
Of course they would use a unified
currency probably pegged to to the
current yuan.
I would. And so I I think you're right.
I think that part of the calculation in
this attack on Iran was to try to
disrupt what so far has been the rapid
growth of of the BRICS countries.
I don't think there's any doubt about
that. I don't think Trump knew what
BRICS were when he entered the second
term but he's found out quickly and he
knows what a threat it is to the United
States. Just the challenging their own
sovereignty against a global
monster like the United States is. What
can do you let's talk about inside the
US right now?
What impact if
they could dress this up as a victory
all they want. And by the way, Netanyahu
yesterday I believe said that it's up to
you Iranian people. We're doing
everything we can and Trump said that
the night that he announced the war as
well when his golfing cap I look like he
just walked off the golf course and he
wasn't really into this war because I
think he was forced into it.
Probably through the reasons we gave
earlier
something to do with blackmail maybe but
he he said, you know, it's up to you.
We're going to do whatever we can. Now,
let's see how you respond. I thought
right away he was setting
the Iranian people up for the failure.
If this doesn't work, we're going to
blame the Iranian people. We we did
everything we could but it was up to you
to overthrow the government, and you
didn't. Netanyahu said the same thing
yesterday. So, I think they're setting
up
an exit there by blaming the Iranian
people.
Yes. We gave them the chance to rise up,
and they didn't. They were probably too
frightened.
Yeah, sure. I could see them saying
that. Hey, I have a question for you, if
you don't mind. Where in the world is
Benjamin Netanyahu? There were reports
that he was in Germany last week. He's
hiding in Cyprus this week. Nobody seems
to know. He He ran away and left his
people to face Iranian bombs and
missiles, and he went to protect
himself, and that seems to be okay with
everybody.
Well, the plane
wing of Zion, let's call which I just
learned their Air Force One
went left Israel right away when the war
began and was flying over the
Mediterranean for a while looking for a
place to land, it looks like, and then
they landed in Berlin. But, there's no
evidence that Netanyahu was on that
plane or that he's in Berlin. Right.
>> They put out videos saying he was
holding a meeting in Berlin, but it was
a cabinet meeting in Israel, but only
Israeli flags. There was no So, I don't
think he's in Germany. I think he's in
Israel. I think he's still alive.
There's all these rumors now. There's a
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. This I just Somebody set
up
a Twitter account that says or an X
account says, "Is Netanyahu dead?"
Question mark.
So, there's all this Somebody sent me an
email, somebody I know, that there's
going to be an announcement Sunday that
he's dead. I mean, I don't buy any of
this.
I think he may be at Mar-a-Lago. If he
goes anywhere, that's where he's going
to be. That's right. [laughter]
And you know,
you know, we're saying saying, "What are
we going to do now, Don?" You know,
"What are we going to
What are we going to do now?" I think
also there's a story that the Israelis
are
prepared for the war in Lebanon.
The other front that they opened to go
longer than the one in Iran. So,
you think there's no chance of a US
ground invasion.
And there's no chance of the US beating
Iran it looks like right now despite
what what
Hex had said this morning, we're kicking
their ass, they are dying, they're
crying for mercy, etc.
So
they have to blame the Iranian people
ultimately and say well we we've knocked
it all out, we destroyed their ability,
you know, they said that they have 90%
reduced their launching of drones and
missiles. That was five or six days ago
and there are
still barrages going on. Yes. Out of the
10% that's that's left? Yeah, as
recently as just two or three hours ago.
Yes.
So they're lying to us and they're going
to have to say, okay, well we did what
we can and we we really defanged them
and we're going to just go on and
concentrate on Lebanon. But the Iranians
again have something to say about this
and there are a lot of people around the
world who want the Israel to
get payback for what they've done to the
Palestinians. There's enormous anger out
there. You could see it on social media
and a lot of joy although because of the
censorship law in Israel which was by
the way a British law under the mandate
that was adopted in '48 by the Knesset
where you can go to jail now for five to
15 years and pay a fine for filming, let
alone putting out on social media
evidence of the damage inside Israel. So
we don't really know what's going on in
Israel about how much they've heard
except a lot of these missiles are
landing. They're getting through.
Yes, they are. So much for the vaunted
Iron Dome. When when a five or 10,000
dollar Iranian drone, a slow motion
drone
can penetrate the Iron Dome,
then you've got a serious problem. And
like I said, you know, if the Iranians
are smart and I think they're very
smart, what they're going to do is just
send wave after wave after wave of
drones,
deplete the Israeli defensive missile
capabilities and then use hypersonics on
what's left?
Absolutely. So,
when
when that happens,
and Iran still has plenty of missiles
left, they have decision to make whether
they're going to go for the kill or let
them walk away from this, declare
victory cuz Trump said on Friday, I
believe, we won in past tense. So, he's
already trying to say that the game is
over. We won.
And they're going to walk away. Will the
Iranians allow them to walk away? Or
will Iran become the graveyard of the US
empire, the way they always said about
Afghanistan? Can Iran
play that role?
Right.
You know, that's really the $64,000
question. If If the Iranians are able to
finish them off, do they finish them
off? And then what about the Samson
option, their directive? Do Do the
Israelis just take everybody with them?
I I wouldn't put it past this
leadership,
you know?
Even even post
Netanyahu, then what do we get? Itamar
Ben-Gvir?
Itamar Smotrich?
They're even worse.
I think it stops there, John, because I
think they would threaten to uh
to use the nuke.
>> think you're right, Joe. I think so I
think you're right. They'll threaten to
do it, and they'll mean it. They'll mean
the threat.
Yeah. You can't take those lunatics
lightly when they say that. As you said,
if Israel's going to go down, they'll
take everyone with them. And they could
even hit Europe as well with their
missiles.
>> Yeah. The Israelis. And they have 200
warheads at least, right? That's right.
But, you know, I asked a person
yesterday who knows about these things.
I said, "I've read that they have
between 50 and 200 warheads." And he
said, "No, I think it's more like 100 to
250 warheads."
Yeah. That's a lot.
>> underground in a base west of Jerusalem.
So, that they're The plutonium is
created and they're fitted in the heads
in Dimona, which the Iranians have I
think threatened to hit with the
hypersonic missile.
But that wouldn't put the end to the to
the warheads they already have in their
stockpile.
I I think that that would be maybe the
end of the war right there. I think Iran
may stop short if that threat is made by
Israel. And then the Israelis and the
Americans will have to lick their
wounds.
Yes. Yes, indeed.
And that could be
not necessarily the end of US
imperialism, but a big bloody nose that
they uh
um
that they could suffer to the US.
And And if I were the Chinese and the
Russians, I would then do everything I
can to arm the Iranians
with as much as they can handle
so that this doesn't happen again. And
Iran would get you'd think Iran will get
a nuclear weapon this time to prevent
I repeat.
I think they would be fools if they
didn't seek one.
Yeah.
John Kiriakou, thank you very much for
spending a little bit of your Saturday
evening with us to talk about this
horrendous uh
situation going on in the Middle East.
And we'd love to have you back on again.
>> I look forward to it. It's always good
to see you, Joe. Okay, John. So, for CN
Live and for The World This Week,
uh and for our producer Kathy Voghan,
and thank I thank you audience, this is
Joe Lauria saying goodbye until next
week on The World This Week.
>> [music]
>> Get out your notebook. There's more.
If you are a consumer [music] of
independent news, and the first place
you should be going to is Consortium
News, and please do try to support them
when you can. It doesn't have its
articles behind a paywall. It's free for
everyone. It's one of the best news
sites out there and it's been in the
business of independent journalism and
adversarial independent journalism for
over two decades. I hope that with the
public's continuing support of
Consortium News, it will continue for a
very long time to come. Thank you so
much.